Hello, and welcome back to another video.
with ItsDrDan.
And today we're going to be learning
how to read a solubility table.
Specifically, this one is designed for
students at my school where we use a
very specific solubility sheet, which
anybody that here is allowed, obviously
allowed to use that's watching this.
Um, but we're going to use
that one in specifically.
So what is it all about?
So solubility is this concept of
how, when we throw an ionic salt.
into water, it has the
possibility to break apart.
Now it all depends on the strength
of the ionic bond and whether or
not the water molecules that are
surrounding it are strong enough to
dissociate and break apart that bond.
So what is this exactly used for?
Well, what we're going to be using this
for is a bunch of different skills that
are really important in the introductory
chemistry and in general chemistry.
So it's mainly used for determining
solubility, so we're trying to figure
out what the states of matter are.
So we want to know is it a solid, is
it a liquid, is it a gas, or can we
actually write that it is aqueous, or
putting an AQ after the chemical species.
So that's one of the most
important things, is can you
figure out if that is the thing?
Because that will tell you the net ionic
equation of these different Species.
Now why is that also important is
because that helps illustrate what
the chemistry is that's occurring
within the chemical reaction.
Remember, chemical reactions are
all about the chemistry of change.
So you need to see like a new molecule
being formed, something being created.
And the easiest way for this to be
illustrated is are we making a solid,
a liquid, a gas when this is happening?
That is one of the biggest things.
So.
In chemical reactions, it's used a lot.
This also helps illustrate oxidation
and reduction reactions, being
that this will help show you the
charge of cations and anions.
And it also helps you figure out this
concept known as electrolytes, meaning
that most of the ones in this table are
considered to be strong electrolytes.
Meaning that they dissolve about
100 percent of the time, whereas
weak is maybe closer to like 5 to
10 percent of the time dissolving.
And non electrolytes just means that,
okay, we have this polar substance
surrounded by a polar substance.
This also helps us get a little bit
of idea of colligative properties,
which is essentially how many ions
are in solution can really affect
how, um, how they behave, uh, when
it comes to their freezing point.
Their boiling point and some
other properties as well.
So we're going to dive into this.
Let's take a look and we'll go
through some different examples
of how this particular thing
works in our chemistry course.
So stay tuned and let's take a look.
Our agenda today is to determine
the solubility of a salt.
Now don't forget what is a salt.
When that is said, well, the
first thing you can think of
is sodium chloride, right?
What you put on your
food every single day.
Salts are a cation and an anion bound
together, meaning that you have a
positive species binding to a negative
species, so ionic characteristics.
So when we're looking at these, what
you're going to be using is, in our
CLELC course, we have the green sheet.
I made a previous video on the
naming component of the green sheet.
This one is on the other
side, the back half.
Which is on the solubility side.
Now what this thing looks like
is essentially you see that
there are two major columns here.
The first one tells you, has a list of
cations and anions that are available
in your whatever compound you have.
And what this tells you is
the different rule sets.
So it's separated into two major parts.
The top part is referred
to as the soluble part.
So how we read these is, let's
say if I have sodium chloride as
an example, and I want to know
is, duh, is it soluble in water?
Well, the way that this works is you
need to break it down into its two
ionic parts, the cation and the anion.
So if you can think, well, what is your
cation, remember that was always written
first, so put Na and then next you're
going to put Cl for the other part.
Now, this is where the solubility chart
comes in handy because what we're trying
to do is see does this happen or not.
So the solubility chart will verify this.
So what we're going to look
for is either chlorine or
we're going to look for sodium.
And what we are going to look at this
first is, alright, if I look at the
very, very first part, I see group one
elements, which is referring to the
first column of your periodic table.
We see sodium plus.
So, what this tells you is we'll
then look at the entire column here.
And one thing you'll notice up here, it
says that it's usually soluble, okay?
And it's soluble except when it's
bound to one of these other elements.
So being that we see sodium is right
here in the middle, so that means
it's soluble unless it's bound to
essentially, well, okay, it says lithium
is slightly soluble unless it's bound
to carbonate, phosphate, and fluorine.
And that's not the case.
So that means it's soluble.
There's another way you can look at
it too is via the chlorine side, which
we see, okay, chlorine's right here.
And what we can do is we see that
chlorine is soluble except when it's
bound to silver, mercury, and lead.
And being that it's bound to sodium, and
it's not one of those three elements,
meaning once again that it's soluble.
So, what we will do is we will write
an AQ next to sodium chloride, meaning
that it's going to dissolve, and the
way that it dissolves is it's going
to turn into sodium and chlorine.
So it's something a little like that.
Let's take a look at another
example using our table.
Okay, so our next example, we have silver
chloride at the bottom of the screen.
And what we're going to do once
again is see, is it soluble?
So what we're going to do is
we're going to write both the
cation and the anion components.
Our cation is silver, and then the anion
in this case is going to be chlorine.
So what we'll do is we're going
to look once again and see if we
see either of those two elements
to find out, is this soluble?
Now, typically you're looking
for the more common element is
what's listed on this table.
So, if you kind of look, you're not going
to see silver anywhere on this list.
That's because it's a transition
metal, it's a, it's a precious
metal, you don't usually see it.
But chlorine, right?
It's a nion that's like in our,
in our blood system, it's in our
body, it's in water that we drink.
It's very common to find in solution.
So once again, we see chlorine here
and it says it's soluble except
for when it is bound to silver.
Ooh, okay.
So we have one, an exception.
So what does that mean is that chlorine
is always soluble except when it's
bound to silver, mercury, or lead.
So, we can't write this then.
What we are then going to do is,
okay, this is not going to happen.
We can erase this here.
And instead, what we are going
to end up doing is putting a
S next to our silver chloride.
And what does that mean?
It stands for that it is a
solid, and in this case it is
a precipitate in the reaction.
Okay, so it's going to, you're going
to see this, uh, solid that's going to
form when you are mixing this together.
Alright, so that's one way to read this.
Let's look at another.
Alright, so let's look
at a third example here.
So we have ammonium hydroxide.
So how exactly are we going to do that?
Well, you've got to
remember your diatomics.
Right.
The first one is NH4 plus, and we are
going to be adding that to OH minus.
Now one thing about ammonium is ammonium
is always soluble no matter what,
but still good to always check this.
So when we're looking at this, we
see ammonium is on the top rule
here, so it is going to be soluble.
And it says, except when
bound to, well, it's only when
lithium is bound to something.
But we can also look at the hydroxide
side to verify this as well.
It should be the exact
same thing for both.
Now the one thing is you will notice
is that hydroxide is down here at
the bottom, and this is where it's
the insoluble area of the table.
Okay, so usually these ones
on the bottom are insoluble.
So if this is to agree with what it said
with ammonium, it should be an exception.
So, what we can look at is, okay, a
hydroxide is insoluble except when
it's bound to group one and ammonium.
So what that tells you is that, all right,
well, this is going to be soluble, and
you can also see it up here, right, except
when bound to ammonium for oxygen as well.
So you notice how it's almost
everywhere we see ammonium.
It's a, it's a big exception rule.
So it's always soluble.
So, what we can do here is that we can
further alter our, our, um, formula,
so we'll put a Q after all these
species to show, hey, this is going to
be soluble, so when we're writing our
ionic equations, let's do another one.
Next one is more just, these next
two, I should say, are just more
to show you some of the basic
rules about the solubility table.
Not everything is going
to be soluble, right?
That's one thing we already saw is
that some things will be solids.
There are a couple others that
you have to be aware of as well.
One is your gases.
So make sure you know
your seven diatomic gases.
So if you ever see them, which are, if
you remember, have no fear of ice cold
beer, which is hydrogen, nitrogen, oxygen,
fluorine, bromine, iodine, and chlorine.
So we see hydrogen and oxygen here.
These are gases, so you never write
them as aqueous, they are always gases.
Now with water, water is a liquid.
So when do we write L's, right?
Aqueous is also a solution.
L is a liquid, which is the same
phase, but there's a difference.
Liquid means that it's pure.
Aqueous means that it's a solution
made in water, so there is a salt.
Dissolved in water, which is what aq is,
but it doesn't really make much sense
to say water is dissolved in water.
We just say it's a liquid, so we
don't use the table for water.
So, keep that in mind for
yourself, write that down.
It's really important to know.
Same thing with your gases, you got
to make sure you're able to denote
solid, liquid, gas and aqueous.
It's very important to
understand what's happening.
Let's look at another
example, just like this one.
Okay, so here we have silver
chloride and it's being formed.
This was the one of the
ones that we did earlier.
It was our second example.
So here I have where you have
silver and chlorine are combining
to make silver chloride.
So chlorine, as I said earlier,
is a diatomic gas, so we
gotta leave that labeled as G.
Another thing is the difference between
the ion and the metal version of it.
So notice here I have silver and
there's no charge listed next to it.
This is extremely important to realize.
There is a difference.
So if there's no charge and it's
a metal by itself, it means that
it's the atomic version of it,
meaning it has a charge of zero.
It's not the ion.
Okay.
So this is not equal to a G plus.
Different from each other.
Okay.
So keep that in mind.
They are not the same.
So if you see just a metal
sitting there in an equation by
itself, it is the solid version.
So you have a solid gas
solid in this equation.
So you don't always use the
solubility table all the time.
You have to use judgment.
This is designed for salt, meaning
it is an ionic equation, right?
So metal.
Okay.
And a nonmetal cation
anion bound together.
Alright, the last thing with your green
sheet is that there are two different
pieces that are included with it as well.
So here I have one of them, the
other is in my gas evolution video.
But here, I have, there's a list of
strong acids and bases that are here.
The important thing to
remember is that these are all
considered strong electrolytes.
Which means that they're all soluble.
Okay, so these are very, very soluble.
Um, and you can see that there's a note
here that says that some of them are
slightly, right, the group 2 elements
are slightly soluble, but the rest of
them are considered strong electrolytes.
They fully dissolve.
So all of these, let's say if I
were to write like, uh, HBr for
example, that's on the left list,
this would break down to H Okay.
MBR minus all these break down
into their ion forms, and that's
how we show all of this list.
All right.
So if you have one of them,
they also break down too.
All right.
So thank you so much for listening.
I hope this video helped a little bit.
It was a little longer than I
originally hoped for, but it's good
to have this kind of information to
help you be able to use the resources
available to you in chemistry course.
Okay.
Thank you so much.
And please hit that like and subscribe
button if you haven't, if you're new to
the channel and I will see you all later.
All right.
Bye now.